<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Basic View</string>
    <string name="deabrat">Deabrat</string>
    <string name="v_2">The placenta has a very large surface area, which facilitates the transport of substances in both directions by diffusion, as described above. Notice that the maternal blood never mixes with the fetal blood — they are always kept separated by the walls of the fetal blood vessels.

5.4.3  The placenta as a filter
One of the functions of the placenta is to act as a filter — allowing beneficial substances such as oxygen and nutrients to pass from the maternal circulation into the fetal circulation, but also trying to prevent harmful substances from making this journey. For example, the placenta allows the passage of some proteins and other bigger chemicals in the blood, including maternal antibodies — chemicals made by the mother to attack any infectious agents, such as bacteria that get into her body while she is pregnant. Allowing her antibodies to pass across the placenta and into the fetus is important in providing protection for the fetus, and later the newborn baby, against the same infectious agents.

However, the placenta cannot prevent the transfer of alcohol, other drugs and viruses to the fetus. These agents can cause birth defects, like discolouration of teeth, bone deformity and brain damage. Advising a pregnant woman to stop taking harmful drugs, and to reduce her exposure to harmful chemicals as much as possible, is very important. Your will learn more about this in Study Session 14 on health promotion issues in antenatal care.

5.4.4  Placental hormone synthesis
The placenta is an important hormone-secreting organ for much of the pregnancy. It secretes human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG), oestrogen and progesterone. The most commonly used pregnancy test detects HCG in the woman’s urine. The purpose of these hormones is to maintain the placenta, to keep it growing steadily as the fetus develops and gets bigger, and to prevent further ovulations and menstrual cycles, so the woman cannot become pregnant again until after the baby is born.

In the next study session, we consider a different interaction between the maternal and fetal anatomy — the bony structures of the mother’s pelvis and the fetal skull.

Summary of Study Session 5
In Study Session 5, you have learned that:

Fertilisation involves the fusion of the male and female sex cells, the sperm and ovum, in the fallopian tubes.
Sperm can survive in the female reproductive system for up to about 72 hours; the ovum lives for only 12 to 24 hours. For fertilisation to occur, sperm must be deposited in the vagina not more than three days before ovulation, or within 24 hours after ovulation.
After fertilisation, cell division starts to form the developing embryo in stages, including the morula (solid ball of cells) and then the blastocyst (hollow ball of cells).
Transportation of the embryo along the fallopian tube to the uterus takes about five to seven days.
Implantation of the embryo takes place in the endometrium (lining) of the uterus. If it occurs in the fallopian tube, it is called an ectopic pregnancy, and this is very dangerous for the woman.
The trophoblast region of the blastocyst penetrates the endometrium, and projections called villi secrete chemicals that dissolve maternal blood vessels. Maternal blood bathes the fetal blood vessels in the placenta, and nutrients, oxygen and dissolved waste is exchanged between mother and fetus.
The maternal and fetal blood never mix in the placenta.
The placenta functions as a transport site, a filter for beneficial and harmful substances, and a hormone-secreting organ.
Self-Assessment Questions (SAQs) for Study Session 5
Now that you have completed this study session, you can assess how well you have achieved its Learning Outcomes by answering these questions. Write your answers in your Study Diary and discuss them with your Tutor at the next Study Support Meeting. You can check your answers with the Notes on the Self-Assessment Questions at the end of this Module.

SAQ 5.1 (tests Learning Outcomes 5.1, 5.2 and 5.3)
Which of the following statements is false? In each case, say why it is incorrect.

A  The energy for moving the sperm’s tail comes from the genetic material in its head.

B  Contractions in the muscular walls of the uterus and fallopian tubes assist sperm to move rapidly towards the ovum.

C  Implantation occurs when the blastocyst burrows into the endometrium and successfully establishes the early placenta.

D  The umbilical vein transports deoxygenated blood from the fetus to the placenta.

E  The placenta acts as a filter, preventing the transfer of all harmful substances from the mother to the fetal circulation.</string>

</resources>